[Music]
This program is brought to you by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.
Michael.
Yeah. The same um
explanation you just gave.
Yeah. Um supposing in the framework of
QFT
and we have a singlet with space
separation of the parts of the
calculation I suppose you say
um is there some sort of virtual
exchange of something?
Um
when what happens under what
circumstance? Well, let's say under the
circumstance that something is measured
at one side,
I wouldn't say so.
I would say nothing happens at the other
side. Nothing detectable happens at the
other side until a message can get
there.
The the degree of entanglement
remains. Whatever you do at the other
end, you may change things at the other
end one way or another, but that
electron which is over there will stay
entangled with the system over here.
It'll stay entangled even though the
system may change. It'll still stay
entangled. Maybe we can work out an
example. Uh maybe at some point I'll
work out exactly the example. Supposing
you um rotated the spin on the right
hand by putting it in a magnetic field.
How does the state vector change for the
two particle system? And is there some
sense in which the measure of
entanglement remains the same? And the
answer is yes, there is. We haven't
talked about measures of entanglement.
Quantitative how much entanglement is
between systems. But as long as those
systems don't start talking to each
other again, there's a measure of
entanglement which never changes between
them even though the particular form of
it can change. Somebody asked me about
what happens if you take an entangled
pair
and you throw one of the particles into
a black hole. Uh what happens to the
entanglement? Well, it becomes entangled
with the degrees of freedom of the black
hole. The black hole evaporates. That
electron over there is still entangled
with all of the photons that come out of
the uh out of the um out of the black
hole and so forth. And in fact, I mean,
you can think of much simpler examples
in black holes or much uh where the
whole story sounds very crazy, but
nevertheless,
forget black hole. Just take a bathtub.
A bathtub. You have a pair of electrons.
They're entangled in the singlet state.
And the bathtub is full of water.
And you take forget electron or atom.
Could be a water atom. Are they water
atoms?
Yeah. Okay.
two two entangled water molecules
and you drop one of them into the
bathtub and it gets all mixed up,
terribly mixed up with all of the stuff
in the bathtub here. This electron is
still entangled not so much with the
single electron which is there but in
the entire state of the bathtub. You
have to now treat the bathtub as a
system and talk about the entanglement
of the bathtub with the electron here.
this electron gets too mixed up with the
others to have a a clear identity. But
nevertheless, the state of the entire
bathtub here stays entangled with the
electron and then the bathtub can
evaporate so that there's no molecules
left. So you uh oh, there's nothing left
to be entangled with. Well, of course
there is. What's left to be entangled
with is all of the um the same uh the
vapor that that escapes out of the
bathtub. And that entanglement will
remain there
frozen in unless something from this
side actually comes over to this side
and they interact with each other again.
Then they can become disentangled. It's
quite possible to take an entangled
state and disentangle it. Anything that
can go one way can go the other way. So
if you were to take two unentangled
electrons, let them interact for a
while, they become entangled.
uh there are anything that can happen
can happen in the opposite direction. So
disentanglement can take place but only
if the systems are close enough to
actually interact with each other. So if
something from over here comes over to
here it can get disentangled but only
then. Yeah.
In the experiments we've been talking
about where you let's say you have
tangled electrons and you're going to
measure on Z-axis or up one down.
When you make both of those measurements
are they still entangle those two
electrons or do the measurements kick
them out?
the measurements kick them out.
Okay. Yeah.
And would one measurement uh disentangle
them?
It can. It can. I'm going to we're going
to we're going to talk about that. Um
those measurements are called
measurements. They're called
observations. And we're going to talk
tonight about how observations or
measurements
uh have the interplay between the
measurement concept, the collapse of the
wave packet, and the concept of
entanglement. I want to get to that. But
before I do, I want to just um spend a
little bit of time because I don't think
I did it very well talking about
projection operators and a little just
just review a little bit of the
mathematics.
Just very briefly
uh
discuss subspaces and um
and the mathematics of subspaces and
projection operators very elementary
level. I don't like to do anything more
advant you know to use more heavy
hammers than are necessary to explain an
idea. All right. First of all, when you
have a space, a space of the kind that
we're talking about, where you have a
concept of vectors and their complex
conjugates, they're formerly called
dual. The bra vectors and the k vectors
are called dus of each other. Uh we're
inclined to sort of think of them as
like complex conjugates. We have a we
have a concept of orthogonality between
those vectors.
As long as we stay in vector spaces
which have finitely many dimensions
instantly first of all what's the
question what's the definition of the
dimension of a vector space the
definition of a of the of the dimension
of a vector space we ought we ought to
give it abstractly forget for the moment
um uh using column vectors and just
counting the number of entries I give
you a collection of abstract vectors
with some orthogonality relations and in
particular some relations of linear
dependence. Linear dependence means that
a vector
may be linearly dependent on some other
vectors.
That would mean that the first vector
can be expanded in terms of the other
vectors. That's what linear dependence
means. That you can write a particular
vector in terms of another subset of
vectors that it's said to be linearly
dependent on it. The dimension of a
vector space is very simple. It's the
maximum number of linearly independent
vectors that you can find in the space.
In other words, in three-dimensional
space, you can find
there are many many triplets of vectors
which are linearly independent. Linearly
independent means that you cannot write
any one of them as a sum of the other n
minus one of them. or an equivalent way
to say it is that you can't find any
linear combination of the vectors which
adds up to zero.
If you can't then those vectors are said
to be linearly independent. Now
obviously there's no way that uh these
vectors are not all in the blackboard.
Incidentally, this one's sticking out of
the blackboard
and those three vectors are not linearly
dependent. They are linearly independent
because there's no linear combination of
them that adds up to zero. Another way
to say it is there's no way to expand
this third one in terms of these other
two. They don't have to be orthogonal to
be linearly independent. If I take three
vectors, I'm not very good at drawing
these things, but take three vectors
which happen not to be orthogonal to
each other. Just those two plus this one
over here where this one is not lying in
the plane of the other two. There is no
way to write the third one in terms of
the other two. So again, they're
linearly deep linearly independent. All
right. Now in a three-dimensional let's
start with a two-dimensional vector
space what's the maximum number of
linearly independent vectors I can find
the answer is two if I add a third one
in the plane
in the plane if I add any third one and
now I'll just draw exactly the same
thing but think of it now as a vector in
the plane
then this third one can be written in
terms of the first two for example we
can add these two and get a vector over
here And then with a minus sign, we're
allowed to have minus signs. We're
allowed to multiply by constants. We're
allowed to add vectors, multiply them by
constants. We can certainly build this
vector from the other two. So these
three vectors that I've drawn on the
blackboard are not linearly independent.
They're linearly dependent. The maximum
number of linearly independent vectors
in a two-dimensional space is two. The
maximum number in a three-dimensional
space is three and so forth.
uh and that's that's the basic
definition of the
dimension of a vector space the maximum
number of uh linearly independent
vectors. Now it's a theorem which we're
not going to prove but it's uh it's it's
straightforward to prove that if you can
in a d-dimensional vector space
d-dimensional vector space with a
concept of orthogonality in it that you
can always find d basis vectors. the
basis vectors the basis vectors mean
that the bas that the vectors are first
of all normalized that means they're
unit vectors and they're all orthogonal
to each other you can find d of them so
in a two-dimensional and in many ways
not just in one way in many ways but in
particular there exist
families of vectors which are orthogonal
mutually orthogonal and unit vectors two
of them in a two-dimensional space three
of them in a threedimensional space and
so forth
and those vectors or a set of such
vectors. Yes.
Uh we have a threepoint particle does it
have the same number?
If we have a three a three what kind of
particle?
particle
three point three particle
a three particle that is a point
particle does it have the same number of
degrees of freedom as the number of
space dimensions?
Uh you're talking about particles moving
in space now.
Yeah. A single particle.
Well, that's a definition. the number of
degrees of freedom is uh yeah we would
say it has the number of degrees of
freedom as but that's not got anything
to do with the dimensionality of the
space of states
nothing whatever
just just for spatial dimensions
yeah just the spatial dimensions right
so the dimensions of the space of states
uh can be very very much larger than the
dimension take a particle moving in a
room
there are three dimensions it can move
in but there's a huge huge number of
possible states of the of the particle
orthogonal states. So they're not
connected in any simple way. Okay. Now
um oh I think I lost this. All right. So
you can always find a mutually
orthogonal set of unit vectors. They're
called basis vectors. They're not
unique, but once you find once you find
the basis, you have a basis. And so
let's imagine then that we have a set of
basis vectors. We'll call them n where n
is a numerical integer that can run from
one
to the dimension of the space.
We have d such vectors
and they're orthogonal to each other
mutually orthogonal. So that means that
m and n gives zero unless m is equal to
n in which case it gives one. So the
symbol for that is the chronica delta
symbol and the chronica delta symbol
simply means the right hand side is one
if m is equal to n and zero if m is not
equal to n. All right so that's the def
that's basically the definition of a
basis set or set of basis vectors for a
uh for a space of the kind we're talking
about.
Now,
um, here's an interesting theorem which
is hardly a theorem. It's more or less
obvious that if you have a basis set, if
you have a basis set which has as many
vectors as there are dimensions in the
space, then it follows that any vector
whatever
can be expanded
as a sum of the basis vectors with
coefficients with a set of coefficients.
Let's call those coefficients a subn
time n sum some n. In other words, this
is just saying that any vector anywhere
can be expanded in terms of uh in three
dimensions the three basis vectors or
whatever.
And now we can relate the um the
expansion coefficients here to the inner
products of these size with the basis
vectors. Let's do that. Just take the
inner product of this equation with any
vector on the left with any one of the
basis vectors on the left. And so we
find that mi
is equal to sum on n a subn m.
Now this is a sum on n but there's only
one term because only when n is equal to
m do we get an answer. Do we get
something non zero? When n is not equal
to m they're orthogonal. when n is equal
to m uh then you get the answer number
just one and so you get only one term in
here and that term is just equal to am
right it's summed on in but we sort of
picked out we've selected out m to
project on to s and the whole answer
then is just am
all right so that's a nice simple fact
that the expansion coefficients here for
a given vector vector are nothing but
the inner products of the s vector with
the basis vectors. That tells us what
the a's are. If we take the uh now I can
rewrite the equation. Let's rewrite this
equation. We now know what the a's are.
Let's write it in the following form. S
is equal to sum on n. And now instead of
writing a, I'm going to write this inner
product. The inner product is just
n s that's a n * n.
I've taken the liberty of writing the
coefficient on the right side of the
vector instead of the left side of the
vector. That doesn't uh you you are
allowed to write 3 * s is equal to s *
3. That doesn't
objection to that.
So this is a number. This is the inner
product. This is the nth basis vector.
It's the same formula except that I've
used for the coefficient here a the
inner product.
Now I have an interesting equation.
I'm going to read this the following
way.
I'm going to read this. I'm going to
separate it in the following way. I'm
going to invent a new symbol. The new
symbol is the sum
of n * n. What on earth does that mean?
We've never defined putting vectors back
to back like that. But now I'll tell you
exactly what such an object is. When you
put vectors back to back like that, any
two vectors, it doesn't have to be basis
vectors. Take any two vectors. Let's
call it A and B.
Put them back to back. What you get is a
linear operator. You get an operator.
And the way that it operates is when it
multiplies a vector,
you just take the inner product of B
with S and multiply it by A. All right?
So this is an object which when you
apply it to a vector with the rule that
you just take the inner product of B
with S, what you get back is another
vector. It's a linear operator.
It's called a diad. A pair of vectors
back to back like that. All diads like
that are linear operators. And we can
now read off from this equation
what this operator is. It's an operator
which does nothing.
When let's move this over a little bit.
Let's put S over well let's think of
this as an operator which hits S.
I've got an extra redundant vertical
sign here, but that's all right. What
does it do? When this construction hits
Sigh, it just gives SI back. So, this
tells you immediately what the meaning
of this object is. It's just a unit
operator.
How do you read it? When this object
over here hits any vector at all, it
gives back the same vector.
And that's
called what it's called is the
resolution of the identity. But anytime
you see this symbol
sum over the vectors of n's back to back
like that, it is just a unit operator.
But in that case, n can't be just any
any
n is summed over. N is a sum over a
basis.
Yes, it has to be a basis. It has to be
a set of orthogonal. We use that here
when we calculated that
the coefficients were equal to s * m. We
use the orthogonality and the unit
character of each one of these vectors.
So yes, we did use that.
These must be a basis,
right?
Excuse me.
Can you call that the
uh
this is just this is just the resolution
of the identity. That's the word for
Yeah, I understand. But if I look at it,
it looks to me like it's with an igen
value one.
Yes.
And the fun.
Yes. The unit operator,
every vector is an igen vector of the
unit operator with igen value one. The
unit operator is a special operator that
has all its every vector is an igen
vector of it and every vector has value
plus one. So it's uh and it just says
that one on any vector gives you back
the same vector.
I I is the identity. It's called the
identity. Good.
All right. But now we might be
interested in a subspace. Let's define
some subspaces, some interesting
subspaces. Subspaces
correspond to certain observable
questions that you could ask or that you
might answer.
So for example, let's suppose that we
have some operator, some observable,
some hermission operator that I'll call
K. It's something that we can measure.
It has an igen value spectrum. It's
hermission that has all the properties
that we identify with an observable
quantity. And let's suppose that we have
a igen vector A of it
with igen value lambda.
That just says that if you measure K
when the system is in the state a you
will get the answer lambda for certain.
Let's suppose there's another igen
vector with exactly the same igen value
not a different igen value the same one
different vector
in fact linearly independent of a. So
it's not pointing in the same direction
as A. It's not a multiple of A with
exactly the same value.
Then any linear combination of A and B,
let's call it alpha A plus beta B,
any combination like that is also an
igen vector of K with exactly the same
value. It's easy to check. you just
apply K to this, but each term just gets
multiplied by lambda. So the lambda
comes on the outside.
Uh if we apply K to it, the K just goes
right through and multiplies each one of
these by lambda. The whole thing is just
a multiplication by lambda. And so any
linear combination of a pair of igen
vectors with the same igen value is also
an igen vector with that igen value. In
other words, What we're what we're
beginning to discover is that there's a
subspace. A subspace ah what does a
subspace mean? A subspace means a set of
vectors
uh which are closed under addition and
which uh which have the property that
they themselves are a vector space but
might be lower dimensional.
The horizontal plane here is a subspace.
It is also a vector space. It consists
of all the vectors in the plane here.
And basically it's all the vectors that
can be built out of the two vectors in
the plane. Same thing here. Any linear
combination of these two vectors will be
an igen vector. And so you can talk now
about the igen space the subspace
the vector subspace of the original
space which corresponds to a particular
value. Okay everybody got that?
states
two states which happen to share the
same property of having a particular
value for some particular variable.
Yeah. For example, here might be here
might be an example. You have up down
the the two particle system up down and
uh up
both of these have the same igen value
for sigma 3. They have different igen
values. Uh no no I heard the same thing
up up. Uh they both have sigma 3 equals
up. Sigma 3 equals + one.
They have different values of tow 3 but
the same value of sigma 3. Right? Any
linear combination of these two also has
the same value for the upness or
downness of the first entry here. Right?
So this the of course there's other
vectors which
down up and down down which have
different values for sigma 3 but these
two span a subspace and it's a subspace
in which sigma 3 is up.
Okay good so that's the idea of a
subspace.
Um you could have a collection of
vectors. It doesn't have to be
two-dimensional. There could be uh 25
vectors all with the same igen value and
then 15 others with different igen
values. But if you pick out all the
vectors
that correspond to a given igen value of
a hermission operator, they form a
subspace. They form a linear subspace
that if you add vectors, subtract
vectors, multiply them by constants,
they are still in the same
uh in the same subspace.
All right. So what that tells us is that
properties such as K equals lambda
that's whatever K happens to be the
property that K equals lambda is not
necessarily identified with a single
vector but is identified with a whole
subspace
question.
Okay.
Now once you've identified a subspace
like this,
you can go a little bit further and find
a basis within that subspace. So here's
some here's some subspace down here
that might have actually
here's some subspace down here
subspace of the floor.
Once we find that subspace, we can find
basis vectors in it. basis vectors that
don't span the whole space but just span
the subspace.
Right? Good. So just think of the
subspace as a space by itself. And we
have a set of uh basis vectors. And I'm
just going to call them A's and B's for
this particular example over here. Let's
call the basis vectors A's and B's
themselves. Assume that we found A, B,
C, however many we need.
It'll be general would be less than D. D
is the dimension of the whole space. But
a set of basis vectors for the subspace
only for the subspace. And those by
definition have the property that any
two of them
are orthogonal
unless they're the same otherwise the
inner product is one. So that's delta A.
But A and B now don't run from one to D.
They run from one to whatever the
dimension of the subspace is.
Good.
So we now have the concept of
a basis for a subspace.
Good.
Let's take that basis and construct out
of it something which looks like this.
Let's take the basis in subspace
and write the expression
sum over a sum over all the basis
vectors in the subspace. What is that
object?
Now the first thing I can tell you is
it is it would give you back the same if
you hit any vector with it,
it'll give you the same vector as long
as the vector is in the subspace. All
right? So if we have a vector in the
subspace for all practical purposes the
other directions don't matter and we're
just re rewriting this kind of formula
over here. If s is in the subspace then
we just get back s again.
But what if s is not in the subspace?
What do you get? If s is not in the
subspace
then what you get is the projection of s
onto the subspace. So, what does that
look like? Let's put this vector over
here someplace
sticking out of the blackboard. I can't
uh don't have enough dimensions to draw
it in properly. The projection onto the
subspace
is the projection of the vector onto the
subspace.
Ah, we just discovered what this object
aa is. It's the projection operator.
It's the projection operator onto the
subspace which in this case corresponds
to the property that K equals lambda.
So this object over here is the
projection operator
onto the subspace in this case where K
is equal to lambda.
That's how you construct a projection
operator. If you have a property that
you're interested in, you find the
subspace which it corresponds to, you
find a basis in that subspace. Now this
is this may or may not be hard to do. I
mean any particular example it may be uh
easy or hard but you find that basis and
then you construct what would have been
the identity operator except it's not
really anymore because it doesn't have
those vectors which stick out of the
plane which stick out of the subspace.
It's the projection operator onto the
subspace.
Yes. Yes. Yes. The identity operator is
a projection operator. It's a projection
operator onto the whole space onto the
whole uh on the whole space. If you only
had one vector here, it would be the
projection onto some particular axis. If
you have two vectors, two dimensional
subspace, it would be a projection onto
a plane. uh if you have uh enough
vectors it actually corresponds just to
a projection back onto the whole space
right but typically it corresponds to a
property
uh the property for the the property
that's associated with the identity
operator is a trivial property just that
the system exists
no information is contained what's that
now every projection operator that
characterizes a property. It's the
property which is true in that subspace.
Why is it the no change observable or
something like that?
I'm not sure what you meant by that.
Okay, I get it.
Observable is a state.
Final
thing about projection operators is the
probability postulate. The probability
postulate for quantum mechanics is most
nicely expressed in terms of these
projection operators. And what we can
say then is if I give you an arbitrary
state side
which is neither which does may or may
not be in the subspace may or may not be
in the subspace. If I give you an
arbitrary normalized state S,
then the probability that S has property
K equals lambda
is just the expectation value of this
projection operator.
Let's see if we can make any sense out
of that. If I plug in for the projection
operator its expression here, what I
find is s a
a summed over a.
Does this make sense? Yeah. It says that
the probability to find a particular
property is the sum of the probabilities
of all the particular ways that you
could find that all the orthogonal ways
that you could find that uh that
particular property.
So for example, if the property
corresponded to the first spin being up,
uh, in other words, if it corresponded
to the projection operator onto the
first spin being up, let's write down
what the projection operator would be.
It would be up up
plus up down
up down.
There are two basis states in which the
first spin is up namely up up and up
down. And if we construct the we we're
leaving out some things here down and so
forth. But this is the projection
operator onto the subspace where the
first spin is up. Okay. Um if I take the
expectation value of any
of this operator in any state, it's the
probability that the first spin is up.
But it comes from two places. It comes
from the probability that the first spin
is up and the second spin is up plus the
probability that the first spin is up
and the second spin is down.
So that's the basic post postulative
probabilities.
Yeah. is the
way we interpret the points in the space
to be probabilities
and the basis vectors of the space to be
the observables or are they the
internal?
No, the observables are the oper are the
operators which have a collection of
values.
The property of having a particular
value is the property
that when you measure K you will
definitely get lambda.
So the property is characterized by an
operator and an igen value.
Okay. A projection operator
is a tool for calculating the
probability
that the property
is really there. In other words, in this
case, it would be the probability that K
equals lambda.
The projection operator is just a tool
and it's a thing whose expectation value
is gi gives that probability.
Yeah. A math question on the left where
you have A and B.
Yeah.
As vectors that have the same value.
Uh I didn't understand if those are
always they always form an orthogonal
basis or you can derive an orthogonal.
Yes, you can find an orthogonal basis.
Yes, do so. Once you've done so, you now
can just think of the other part the
other directions in the space as being
incidental. You now have a space with a
set of vectors within it that form a
basis
over there where you have them as being
orthogonal. Then then you're saying
those are a and b are basis vectors that
third
basis vectors for the subspace.
For the subspace
only for the subspace
only for the sub. Would it be correct to
label those two bottom axes?
Yeah. As a and b. Yeah, this could be a
equals one. Well, yeah, I I have a funny
notation here. This could be a and b.
Yeah.
And then the side would be the one
that's sticking up.
So, so I could be any vector
and the projection is is
and then in this case there's a third
vector which does not lie in the
subspace. You could add it in as a basis
vector for the whole space, but it's not
part of the subspace.
Right? And then when you project s onto
a and then project s on to b and add the
answer you get the projection onto the
subspace itself.
So can I interchange a and b there?
Yeah. In this
when you say k equal to lambda it
shouldn't be uniquely a right. It could
be also b vectors
where where
yeah in which equation
in the first equation
this one here.
Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. This is just okay. In this
equation here, I'm really talking about
a particular vector, right? In this
equation, I'm talking about a sum of a
vector. So, I really should I really
should use a different notation.
Uh this is a summation variable here.
And we can call it sum over a prime or
something like that.
We can we can decorate it with as many
indices as we want and it'll just get
very confusing. But when you see a sum
like this, don't think of a particular
vector being picked out. Think of
summing over all the vectors. Whereas an
equation like this without a summation,
it means some specific uh some specific
vector.
Right. Right. This could be a sum over a
and b. Right. Right. A prime could stand
for a or b or c or d depending on how
many vectors there are. Exactly.
I didn't want I didn't want to make too
many notations. I didn't want to put sub
subscripts on uh on notations, but yes,
you got the idea. Summation index like
this here is just a sum over something.
Here you've picked out the A vector and
the B vector. Uh you could have called
it one and two. Fact, that would have
probably made more sense to just call it
one and two.
Um
okay, any other questions?
Just double check the probability
amplitude.
No, probability.
Yeah, these are probability amplitudes
indiv. These are probability amplitudes.
Multiplying them by their complex
conjugates give you probabilities and
then summing over the different ways
that you could get. You see, there are
different ways that you could get K
equals lambda. You could have it in one
vector or the other vector or the other
vector. uh summing over all the various
ways gives you the total probability for
K equal to lambda. That answer the
question. Yeah. Good. Okay. Good. Good.
Just anymore. Okay.
All right. So that's that's another way
of stating the fundamental uh
uh probability
postulate.
Now if we have two commuting
projection operators, two commuting
projection operators mean
um
well
means exactly what I said two commuting
projection operators
and I'll give you some examples in a
moment.
Let's call it P
uh
K= lambda and another projection
operator for another property. Let's say
L equals mu.
These are two distinct projection
operators for two distinct properties.
If they have the property that they
commute, then there's some simple
definitions that you can make of what
you mean by and and or.
What about and?
What is the projection operator for K
equals lambda and L equals mu?
What are the what is the projection onto
the simultaneous condition that both k=
lambda and lals mu? In order for there
to be an and and to get any answer,
there have to be vectors in common in
the two subspaces mean the two subspaces
have to intersect with each other. They
have to intersect. So if you had two uh
two spaces which didn't intersect at all
except at the origin. All subspaces
always intersect at the origin. So
there's two subspaces which don't
intersect except at the origin.
then and let's let's uh let's let's
place this one vertically upward just
for simplicity
then clearly there are no states which
share the property associated with this
projection operator and with this
projection operator there's nothing in
common between them on the other hand if
we had two
uh subspaces
which
shared another subspace a lower
dimensional subspace space. Then there
are vectors in the space which share
both properties
which have the property associated with
subspace number one and the property
associated with subspace number two. And
we can ask which
vectors which states of the system have
both property one and property two.
And what is the projection operator for
the and statement for the property k=
lambda and l= mu?
Well, the answer is the product of the
two of them. If they commute, if they
commute, the answer is the product of
the two of them.
Uh let's see if we can see why that's
so.
Let me just call this pk. I'm not going
to call it pk equals lambda. That's too
much notation. just P K and P L. Now if
they commute, it doesn't matter which
order you write them down in.
Let's take any vector whatever. Oh. Oh,
let's go back a step. Can I go back a
step? Yes, I'm going to go back a step.
If you take
the projection operator PK
and you apply it to any vector at all,
whatever, apply it to any vector at all,
you will get a vector in the subspace.
Right? So it stands to reason then that
if you take this whole vector here, it
must be an igen vector of K with igen
value lambda.
This is a vector in the subspace K
equals lambda.
And so it must be the case that K on
this
just gives you lambda
* PK
S. This isn't very deep. It just says
that PK on S gives you a vector in the
subspace where K is definitely equal to
lambda.
Okay. Now let's take the product PK * PL
apply it to any state whatever
I say that this vector will have both
the property
that K is equal to lambda and L is equal
to mu how do we check that well I have
first of all I told you that if you take
any state and multiply it by PK it'll
have the property K by property K I K
equals lambda.
Let's just call it the property K.
Any
vector if you multiply it by PK has the
property K. Well, here's a vector.
I've multiplied it by PK
on the left. Therefore, it has the
property K.
But if it's also true that PK and PL
commute with each other, I can also
write this as P L time PK
on S. And now I exhibit the fact that it
has the property L. So if I have two
commuting projection operators, two
projection operators which commute with
each other, that roughly means that the
uh that the two observables are
compatible with each other, that you can
measure both of them independently, that
you can measure them both
simultaneously,
then the product of the two projection
operators corresponds to the and
statement.
In other words, it corresponds to
finding that corresponds to vectors or
it responds excuse me to uh to the
projection onto the simultaneous
property kals lambda k lals mu for
example if I wanted to know the
probability that k equals lambda and l=
mu it's just the expectation value of
the product
s
p k
l
is the property is the probability not
just that K equals lambda or that L
equals mu but that K equals lambda and L
equals mu. Okay, that's the and
statement. You multiply projection
operators.
There's also an or statement. The or
yeah
also known as well in classical logic it
would be the intersection. Uh I'm not
sure that you call it the intersection
in vector spaces but it is it is the
intersection in that sense. Yeah. In
classical logic, it would correspond
exactly to that to the if you have a
property described by a uh by a subset
of uh points in a in a set and you have
another property, then it's the
intersection which corresponds to the or
statement.
Sorry, the and statement.
The or statement corresponds to the sum
of the two projection operators. I'll
let you try to prove that yourself. and
is product or is sum. So if you're
interested in what vectors either have
the property that k equals l k equals
lambda or l= mu the or statement then
the projection operator happens to be
the sum of them. But we're going to be
more interested I think in the product.
If they're not compatible you just get
hash. You can't measure both things
together.
I think it's the clearest that they're
compatible. They're not compatible. You
can still define it, but uh
um it's not a very good definition.
What's that?
Okay. the spin of one. If you have a two
electron system,
this any component of one spin is
compatible with any other component of
the other spin.
We could check that
spin in charge. This could be another
one. Yeah. All right. But let's check
let's uh let's take the case of two
spins. I have a bunch of let's see um
yeah
because the spin operators act
completely independently
on the two sets of degrees of freedom
they always commute with each other. If
you first multiply this vector by some
sigma and then multiply it by a tow you
get exactly the same answer as if you
first multiply it by tow and then sigma.
So usually very often
um compatible operators are simply
operators for two separate subsystems.
When you build subsystems uh by by
putting systems together any quantity
associated with one subsystem is
automatically compatible with the
quantities for another subsystem.
That's an example.
By subsystems you really sort of mean
degrees or types of freedom that add
degrees of freedom.
Yes.
and spin for us. So those were
well momentum and spin happen to be
compatible.
Yeah. Yeah. But they could belong to the
same electron.
Uh but if you have two distinct
electrons and anything associated with
one electron is automatically compatible
with the other electron.
On the other hand, there can be things
associated with a single electron that
are compatible. For example, if an
electron is moving in threedimensional
space, the components of position X, Y,
and Z are also compatible with each
other. We haven't spoken about that
because we haven't done that kind of
quantum mechanics. We're doing bit
quantum mechanics and not particle
quantum mechanics.
Uh
but the simplest situation for
compatibility
is uh when um when uh two things belong
to two different let's call them cubits.
In the case of cubits and the case of
simple spins
the criteria would be that they belong
to different spins. They're associated
with different spins and they're
compatible.
No no no no no something good. something
which is not compatible would be the x
component of one spin and the y
component of the same spin.
You can't measure the x component of a
spin and the y component of the spin at
the same time.
Uh
so they're not compatible.
You only got one one magnet one
direction that you can put the magnetic
field in to measure the spin of a
particular electron. You can't put the
magnetic field simultaneously in two
directions and try to and try to measure
two different components of the same
spin. On the other hand, if you have two
electrons and the simplest situation is
just take them apart, put one magnetic
field over here in one direction,
another magnetic field over here in
another direction and you can measure
two different components of two
different spins. So they become
compatible. But two components of the
same spin are not compatible.
That just is the same way as saying
different matrices they don't.
Yes. It's just a statement that sigma
matrices don't commute.
Is that what you're saying?
Yes. When you see these two
Yep.
that proves that
that's all you need.
That's all you need. Absolutely.
Absolutely. Yeah.
The position and momentum don't commute.
Position and momentum don't commute.
That's another excessive,
right? Position. Although the position
Yes. position.
Exactly. All right. So, we have the
concept of and and then let me just
remind you I I just wanted to go through
this again to make the logic uh clear
what we did last time.
I sort of um implicitly
pretty much assumed everything that I've
done tonight when I when I described it.
and it may have left you
less than comfortable with the
procedures. Let me just remind we're not
going to go through the calculation
again. Just going to remind you what we
did. This was the uh the Bell
inequality. Well, first of all, we
proved the completely classical theorem.
The completely classical theorem had
nothing to do with quantum mechanics and
it's not even true in quantum mechanics.
It says if we have some properties A, B
and C, the number of uh of quant number
of objects which have A but not A and
not B plus the number of objects and
number of objects could also stand for
probabilities.
Number of objects with B but not C
is greater than or equal to the number
of objects with A and not C.
Now we can apply this
if the If electrons were strictly
classical objects, we could apply it
just to electrons and take A, B, and C
to be the following quantities. A could
stand for
electron
Z component of the electron, the third
component of the electron up. And I'll
just indicate it by pointing uh an arrow
up. That's A.
B could be that the electron is pointing
along 45 degree axis in the 13 plane
could be simple to be simple and C could
be that the um electron is lying along
the horizontal axis that if you measure
along the horizontal axis you definitely
get up not A, B and C or in particular
not B and not C would correspond to the
electron pointing in the opposite
direction. So if B corresponds to
electron pointing in this direction then
not B corresponds to it pointing in the
opposite direction.
Can can I ask a question about say up
and down? Okay up up and down areal
but uh up is not minus down there two
different things. Okay is that
minus and that just plus and minus just
something that happens in the
calculations. Yes.
And doesn't have a physical
sometimes it sometimes influence the
vector a plus b might be quite different
than the vector a minus b. And I gave
you an example up down minus down up is
quite different than a up uh you know
the sign can make a difference but the
overall sign never does.
Okay.
If bel theorem gets violated for any
quantum properties of anything or only
for certain ones and in which cases
um I don't I don't honestly know the
complete answer to that question um
uh it's certainly not
violated for any state for example I can
find states of the two particle electron
system for the bell inequality will be
satisfied for
So the answer is that there are
certainly states for which the belly
inequality is satisfied. You have to
search a little bit to try to find
situations where it's violated. But it's
not very hard. If you just uh throw, you
know, just take a random guess. Uh I
don't know 6040. 60% of the times you'll
satisfy the inequality, 40% you won't. I
just made that up. I have no idea
really. But uh but uh but most likely I
would guess that it's more likely if you
randomly selected a state that the
inequality would be satisfied and that
it's a sort of smaller percentage of the
uh space of states that doesn't satisfy
the inequality. But I never checked
that. That's something uh
you can set B up to be an angle theta.
Yes, you could. You could. And then you
could check it. You could check it as a
function. Yeah.
Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And you could also
have C be an angle. And I would guess if
the angles are too close together that
the that you don't uh that you don't
violate the inequality. But we can check
that. That's an interesting thing to
check. At what angles is the inequality
satisfied? At what angles is it
violated?
[Music]
Could be. Yeah. I I haven't checked it,
but uh
you're talking about photons, I think.
Talk about photons or electrons.
Okay. So, that's a it's a little bit
different, but uh yeah. Yeah, there's
certainly situations where the
inequality is not violated.
Um but uh but let me just remind you
what we did. All right. Then we we what
we did was take a two electron system
and we imagine doing many many checks.
The two electrons are in the singlet
state. We do many many checks on this
and every single time we find out that
when
um that the if we measure the spin of
one of them along any axis the spin of
the o of the other one is along the
opposite axis.
That would suggest
that the property B that the property
not B the property not B for electron
one is the same as the property B for
electron 2.
In other words, it would suggest that
the property not B which says that
electron one is bound is equivalent to
the property B for electron number two.
So we could rewrite this inequality then
as if we work in terms of pairs of
electrons. We have these pairs of
electrons which have been created.
They've been created in a way that the
spins are always anti-aligned
and we can substitute for the property A
and B. We can first of all A can still
be associated with electron one. uh A
and not B would then become the number
of pairs
where the first electron is up but the
second electron
is at 45°. The second electron being at
45° would would imply that the first
electron was in not B if it made sense
to talk about A and not B for electron
number one. So that's this one over
here. Let me uh Well, I'm sorry. Uh, not
B should be minus 45. The other pair
not B means the electron is pointing
this way. But if electron one is
pointing this way, electron 2 is
pointing along B. So not B for electron
one is B for electron two.
Right. Good. Right. Not something for
electron one since they're opposite.
Since they're opposite, any not
statement for one becomes the uh the
positive statement for the other. Good.
All right. So we can now rewrite this
inequality
as
uh the number of
pairs in which the first spin is up but
the second spin is along 45°
plus the number of pairs in which the
first spin is at 45°
but the second spin is at 90°
is greater than or equal for the number
of sp of pairs where the first spin is
up and the second spin is at 90°.
All we have to do to check the
inequality for any given state is to
construct the projection operators for
these properties. Now this is a two
electron system. Now we've replaced the
one electron system by a two electron
system. If we were doing classical
physics with classical logic, the
opposition of the two spins would tell
us that not B is the same as B for the
second spin. So that's the logic here.
Now, okay. So what are the projection
operators? We take any state whatever
and we can ask
what's the probability for this
property? What's the probability for
this property? What's the probability
for this property? So let me go back
now. We want to construct the projection
operator for this property.
This property has spin number one
pointing up. The projection operator for
that is 1 + sigma 3 over two.
If the first spin is up, sigma 3 gives
plus 1 + 1 is 2 / two. That's one. Okay.
So yes that's uh if this first spin is
down then sigma 3 is minus one 1 + minus
1 is zero and we get zero. So this is
the projection operator onto the first
spin up. The projection operator onto
the second spin pointing in it along its
axis is also a one plus something but
not 1 plus sigma but 1 plus towa because
toao is a spin operator for the second
electron but not tow along the third
axis but tow along the 45°ree axis.
What is that? That's tow 1 plus tow 3
over the of 2. That's the
projection of toao onto the 45 degree
axis and then we should divide it by
two.
This is the projection operator for one
statement. Spin number one is up. The
projection operator for the other
statement spin number two is along 45°
is this one. What is the projection
operator for the and statement that
electron number one is up and electron
number two is along 45 degrees. It's the
product.
It's the product. So, we multiply these
two operators together. Dot just means
multiplication.
We do the same for this one. Same kind
of thing for this one. I should move
this over a little bit. But the second
projection operator, let's put it over
here.
Would be the first spin along 45°.
That's 1 + sigma 1 + sigma 3 over 2
all / 2.
But then the second spin along the
horizontal axis. So that's 1 + 1 / two.
That's the projection operator for the
second configuration. And the projection
operator for the third configuration
is 1 + sigma 3 / 2 times 1 + 1 / two.
Well, we know how to work with these
sigma and tow operators. And if I give
you any state, any state of the two
electron system, you can calculate the
expectation value of these three
projection operators. And you can simply
check is the expectation value of this
one plus the expectation value of this
one bigger or is it not bigger than the
expectation value of this one over here.
This is the exercise that we did last
time for the singlet state.
singlet state up down minus down up and
we found that the inequality was
violated.
Um there is no reason why it should not
have been violated. We're not doing
classical set theory. The derivation of
this formula here came from drawing
various classical sets and looking at
the uh just you know just counting up uh
which uh what things corresponded to A
and not B, what things corresponded to A
and not B. what regions corresponded to
B and not C, what regions corresponded
to A and not C. It didn't have to do
with the intersections of projection
operators. It had to do with the
intersection of sets. So there was no
reason why the inequality should have
been satisfied in the quantum context
and it's not.
If we know that for a particular system
the belch theorem either violated or not
violated
for a particular system in a in a
particular state
right in a particular state
that's right
then is there anything more we can say
about it or or nothing other
the only thing you can say about it is
this is a very clear demonstration that
quantum mechanics can not be the
statistical theory of some kind of
system system with classical that's
really governed by classical logic by
classical set theory that's all that you
learn out of it but it cannot be and uh
so if a particular quantum state
actually satisfies Bell's theorem yeah
can we say that it's some sort of it's
more classical than not in in any way
I think you probably maybe
um
remember there are many many variables
that you could check in this case. Well,
um
Bell's inequality may car you may be
able to check very very many different
uh inequalities for the same system. So
by choosing properties by choosing a
particular set of three properties you
might find for a certain system in a
certain state that the inequality is uh
is not violated but then choose some
other properties for the same system you
might find it is and I suspect that
would generally be true. I think that
would probably always be true that you
could probably always find properties A,
B and C that the inequality would be
would be violated.
There's a there's a later
Okay, I'm having difficulty trying to
figure out what kind of an experiment
this describes. How many magnets and
populations of electrons and
Yeah, good. Okay, so that's that's the
right question to ask. At this point, we
have a beam of particles, but the
particles come out in pairs. They come
out in correlated pairs.
Uh here's how we might start. We might
start with a pair of electrons. the pair
of electrons are near each other.
Because they're near each other, they
interact with each other. And the lowest
energy state happens to be the singlet
state. And so after a while, they either
do or don't emit a photon, but they get
into this singlet state. Then the
electrons are taken apart.
And that's not too hard to do. I mean,
you can send them through some sort of
uh system which separates them. It could
be an electron and a posetron. You put
them in a field. The field sends the
electron one way, sends the positron the
other way. And so you have well
separated a well separated pair. But not
just one of them, many of them. Many
such pairs. For each pair that you've
made,
there they are. You measure
uh you take
divide them up into groups. divide them
up into groups so that we can do three
separate experiments. Okay, so we have a
100red billion pairs. We take a third of
them and on the third of them we're
going to measure the number of A and not
B.
How much is a third of 100 billion? 100
billion divided by three. We take 100
billion divided by three of the pairs.
And in the first set we measure the up
component of the electron, the vertical
component of the electron and the 45
degree component of the posetron.
Okay.
And we count up alto together. How many
pairs are there in which the first
compon the the electron the first
electron was up along the three axis and
the second electron was up along the uh
the 45 degree axis. Okay. I mean that
gives us a probability that gives us the
probability forget ins we can just use
probabilities here. That gives us the
probability that the first electron is
up and the second electron is along 45
degrees. Then we take the second uh
group and do exactly the same thing
except in the second group we don't
measure the first electron up and the
second electron at 45°. We make the
second electron at 45 degrees. Sorry,
the first electron at 45 degrees and the
second electron at 90 degrees. We count
up the probability for that.
we add it. And then finally, we take the
last third of the electron pairs of the
electron posetron pairs and measure the
first electron up along the Z-axis and
the second electron along the horizontal
axis and count how many of them have the
property that the first electron is up
or what what percentage have the
probability that the first electron is
up and the second electron is
horizontal.
theorem says classically classically if
it were true it would say that this plus
this should be greater than this
but your but your theorem is dealing
with a single population and this is
three different populations
you can take it as dealing with
probabilities
and since we have a a identically
selected set of uh three populations
we can measure the probability
distributions by looking at just the uh
separate uh
the theorem would be true if we divided
the system identically prepared assuming
they're identically prepared
uh all three populations in fact every
single pair here
uh the theorem would be true about these
subopuls also
as long as you prepared them in the same
way. That's right. as long as you
prepared them in identical ways.
So
yeah,
in the year 2000, Alan Aspect
um wrote an article commemorating John
Bell. In there, there's this very neat
diagram that shows basically the
distribution that you can expect
versus what you get quantum
mechanically. And it shows how the
quantum mechanical results include some
data points which are outside of the
classically uh or inside the classically
excluded region.
Mhm. I haven't seen it. But uh 191 19
when
I don't understand why you can't use
this to signal
the two electrons would be going across
going apart very slowly.
And so if I
measures one of them
they're slowly could measure it and send
a message saying I just measured this
years to
right that was that was as far as I
understand aspect experiment
was done in such a way that the second
that the two um that the two
measurements
could not that a light signal could not
have been sent between them.
No,
no. If there was time for a light signal
to go from one to the other,
then it would not be a contradiction.
You might wonder how the hell did the
signal get across there? Uh what was the
mechanism? Who sent the light beam and
so forth, but you wouldn't have a
contradiction with causality or with
locality or whatever you want to call
it. If the second electron was measured
after a time during which a light beam
could have gone from one place to
another, you might say, "Oh, I've I
didn't see any light beam go. I must
have discovered some new force of nature
that I didn't notice before, but at
least it doesn't exceed the speed of
light."
Um,
but the trick is to do the experiment in
such a way that a light signal could not
have gone to the second electron when
you measure it from the first electron.
I don't think he used electrons. I think
he used photons incidentally. But uh
I think the way aspect had put it was
that um in order for the classical
explanation to match the quantan
right that's the other way to say it.
Right. And that's right. That's exactly
right.
So part of this whole queerness of this
entanglement
is connected with signals not going
faster than the speed of light. When
people say that in order to have hidden
variable theories and that means
classical logic systems which can
somehow mock up the effects of quantum
mechanics when they say they have to be
non-local what they mean is that signals
have to be able to go faster than the
speed of light to uh to send messages
between the two electrons. I want to get
to another thing and we're not going to
get to it, but uh yes, we are going to
get to it. Yeah. I'm not going to I'm
not giving you any uh freedom to run
loose in the hallways.
There's nothing sacred about the
No, no. Uh that's right. There's there's
nothing um sacred about conserved
quantities in this context here. It's
just a
a nice very simple system to work with.
In fact, these don't even really have to
be spins. They could be any two system
any system that has two states, an upper
and a level atomic state.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
No, it was not important that this was
that spins are angular momenta or
anything like that. No, not at all. All
right. What I wanted to do next
was to talk about
the connection between
three things.
Interference phenomena,
measurement phenomena or how you do what
a measurement means and its connection
with entanglement.
How a measurement is really the
establishment of entanglement between
systems. That's what a measurement is
and how measurements destroy
interference.
How they It's called the collapse of the
wave packet. So, I thought we would get
to that next. And let's see. Let's see
how far we can go. Uh we may want to
come back to it if I don't. Uh
so what we're actually going to be
speaking about
is the two slit experiment
but I'm going to simplify the two slit
experiment
so that we can think about it as just
having a finite number of states uh a
little simpler than the two slit
experiment. It is the two slit
experiment but uh we'll just imagine
that a photon or an electron or whatever
it happens to be no spin forget spin.
Now these are real particles they really
move from one place to another but let's
suppose that the uh the particle could
be in any one of several vertical
locations
just to make life simple.
some set of we'll call this 0 1 2 3 -1
- 2 -3.
So the electrons I'll call it an
electron but forget it spin. It starts
out at zero and this is the ver this is
the position of the electron along the
vertical axis. The electron is actually
going to move to the right. It might
also move up or down. But I'm just
simplifying by giving it only a finite
number of places where it can live just
so that we can use the tools that we've
been talking about of finite dimensional
spaces. So the number of possibilities
where the electron can be is finite. In
this case, seven of them. All right, the
electron moves over to the right. Uh
let's uh there are also seven places
where it can uh where it can be found
over here.
actually from this side over here I'm
going to select out and assume that the
electron started at this point here. So
the electron actually starts at zero.
Now it goes over to here and when it
gets over to here it's in one of these
seven places depending on which place
it's in. Well not depending on which
place it's in. It continues to go and it
continues to go over to a third place
which also has the same set of uh 1 2 3
4 5 6 7 the same set of possibilities.
We're really talking about the evolution
of a system from one instant of time to
another instant of time. But here's the
game we're going to play. It is a
two-slit experiment. I'm going to assume
that if the electron arrives at this
point that it just gets sent back.
All right. So, we're going to ignore the
possibility that the electrons which go
backward. If it goes to this point over
here, it also gets bosses back. It only
goes through if it hits this point or
that point. So, from the point of view
of a two-slit experiment, I've opened
this slit and I've opened that slit and
I've sent an electron to here or to
here.
one electron at a time. We're sending
one electron at a time. It either goes
through the upper slit or the lower
slit. And if it goes through the upper
slit, it can go
well, it can go through either slit and
arrive at any one of these places over
here.
So forth.
I'm interested. I'm going to give you
some. We're going to make up some rules.
rules that are consistent with quantum
mechanics.
Uh a simple example, I'm interested in
the end in the probability that the
electron arrives here, here, here, here,
or here, or here. What's the probability
under various circumstances?
Now, here's the assumption.
The evolution of systems, the quantum
mechanical evolution of a system is
linear.
That means that if a system starts in a
state a
and evolves to a state a prime, in this
case it could be that it starts at any
one of these places here and gets to any
one of these places here. And if the
state B would evolve to B prime,
then if we start the system in the state
A plus B,
it will evolve into A prime plus B
prime.
This is the assumption of linearity. In
fact, we can do this with arbitrary
coefficients alpha beta.
That's the statement that states of
systems evolve in a linear way. That
linear superpositions evolve into linear
superpositions. Now, this is an
experimental fact. As I said last time,
it's very, very hard, maybe quite
impossible. Nobody has ever succeeded in
changing quantum mechanics a little bit
without coming to really silly
conclusions. So we'll take it as a
postulate that the evolution of state
vectors is linear. Linear superposition
evolves to the same linear superposition
with the same set of coefficients.
All right, let's that's that's about all
I'm going to assume and we're going to
well make some definitions. Now I'm
going to start the electron over here
and after a certain time it will have
arrived at one of these places. I'm not
interested. I might as well throw away
all the places which just reflect the
electron backward because I'm not even
going to look for it back here. So it
either gets to one or to minus one.
And by symmetry
by symmetry just the up down symmetry
here if I really do have enough down up
down symmetry if the length of this path
is exactly the same as the length of
this path and so forth and I start the
electrons symmetrically about the only
state that I can get to over here is the
linear combination. So we can write it
this way. We can say starting with zero
the state will evolve to the state one
plus minus one. Now I'm not terribly
interested in normalizing the state. I'm
not interested in keeping track of prob
total probability here. That's not going
to play any big role in what we're going
to say. So if we start with the electron
over here after a time by the time it
gets to the slits over here it will be
in a superp position of states with
equal amplitude with equal likelihood of
being here and here
just because of the symmetry of the
problem you would expect equal
coefficients here.
But now let's say what happens if an
electron starts at one.
What happens to it when it goes over to
this side over here? So let's make a
postulate or an assumption about that.
If it starts at zero initially, it gets
to 1 + 1 prime or minus one. 1 plus
minus one. What happens if it starts at
one over here or minus one over here?
What happens to the state vector over
here? So let's make the following
assumption. If you start at one, if an
electron starts at one, then by the time
it gets over, we can call this the
screen over here. It's where we measure
the electron, the screen. By the time it
gets to the screen over here, I'm going
to make an arbitrary assumption that it
is in the state of summation s
n.
It has to be some linear combination
of these are basis vectors. They
correspond to orthogonal configurations.
These are different places. They don't
get mixed up with each other. If an
electron is over here, it's not here. If
it's here, it's not here. So, we have
these basis vectors n and this is about
the only thing I can write down. Sorry,
not one is equal but one goes to
that one becomes after a further
interval of time it becomes some linear
combination.
But it's not the same state either. I
mean you got
it's not the same state.
You got n there and you got a one but
you really mean two different
notation not distinguishing between the
second and third
between where and where.
So you've got a one for your
this one corresponds to starting over
here
like prime or something like that on
your under
your statement
over here.
Yes, I could but I didn't want to
decorate it with too many uh symbols. So
just this goes to just uh just once I
once I put an arrow there I don't have
to uh be so uh I'm not writing anything
as equal to anything else. I'm just
saying the state one over here will
evolve into some state s.
What happens if it starts at minus one?
Well, if it starts at minus one,
it'll go to some other combination. I'm
not even going to tell you what
combination it is other than to say it's
some other f*
n
minus one.
These are arbit these are arbitrary
linear combinations over here. They
could be determined by experiment. They
might be determined by mathematics. But
I've written down the most general
possibility that if you start at one
over here, you will get to some linear
combination characterized by a set of
coefficients. If you start at minus one,
you will get to some other linear
combination. I won't even tell you what
they are. What happens if you start in
the initial state one plus minus the the
linear combination of both of these?
Then the linearity postulate tells you
that at the end the final state will be
the sum over n of the sum of these two
which is fn plus n
times n.
In other words, by the time you get over
here, the coefficients will be the sum
of the coefficients that you would get
by going through the upper root and
going through the lower route. Right?
If you go through the upper route, in
fact, even if you closed off the lower
route, then the experiment would only
involve one going to c here. If you
closed off the lower route, if you
closed off the upper root, the
experiment would only involve going from
minus one would involve this combination
over here. If you open them both and
allow the electron to go either way,
then the rule is the linearity of
quantum mechanics tells you that you
should add the state vectors. If you
start with a linear sum of two vectors,
you should add the two in the final
state. So you get to here
question.
Yeah.
Is
are those normalized on the right side?
It doesn't
because
if one of them is way bigger than the
other. It doesn't make any sense. You've
got you got to do something.
Why does it make any sense?
Well, I mean c could be in the billions
and f could be very small if you
normalize. It could be
for example if you put some obstruction
here which only let very few electrons
through we could make the uh the fives
be much smaller than
I'm just suggesting that that you
haven't said what the units are. I mean
one could be in meters and the
wait wait wait wait. Size and fs are
dimensionless objects. They're squares
of probabilities.
I know but they have a scale they have a
scale factor associated with them that
you normally take out. Yeah, we can
normalize them.
I didn't bother normalizing them over
here. At the moment, I didn't want to
worry about keeping track of total
probability. All right, that's that's
that's something we'll do next time.
That's called unitarity. And I don't
want to worry about it right now. Uh
whether it's normalized or not
normalized is not so important. The
important thing is that uh that you get
the sum of the
coefficients going through the upper
root and the lower root. And that's the
postulative linearity
that if you evolve from one you get s if
you evolve from minus one you get phi.
If you evolve from the state one plus
minus one, I don't like to say one for
this state plus this state, then you get
the sum of the two. That's the posture
of linearity. What's the probability
then at the end of the day that you
measure the electron at the nth or the
mth the mth site?
Well, these are the coefficients that
add up to give you the state vector.
This is an orthonormal basis. It's quite
clear that the probability
the probability that you land on the m
site over here is just s m + 5 m complex
conjugated times m + 5 m.
We could either do this through
projection operators or just use the
simpler statement that the squares of
the coefficients. We take the
coefficients here. We complex conjugate
them and square them. And that gives us
the probability that we arrive at the
mth site.
M could be 1 2 3 and four. And this
would give us the various probabilities
for arriving at different places. Notice
what we get. We get four terms when we
work this out. we get si star of m si of
m.
Now what is that?
That's all we would have if we closed
off the second hole. If we only had the
first hole open,
the answer would just be si star m.
So what this is is the probability that
had we closed off the second hole, we
would have arrived at the m n m n m n m
n m n m n m n m n m n m n m n m n m n m
n m n m n m n m n m n m n mth place.
On the other hand, there's also five
star.
That's the probability
that if we closed off the top opening
and went through the bottom one, we
would have arrived at the mth place.
Classically, that's all there would be.
The probability to go from here
to here by one of two roots would just
be the sum of the probabilities of going
through the upper route and the lower
route. That's all you would have in
classical physics.
If you had a random walking particle
that random walked around, you left a
upper hole open, you would have a
certain probability to get here. If you
left the low up hole open, you would
have a different probability to get to
the same place. If you left both holes
open, the probability would just be the
sum of the two probabilities.
But in quantum mechanics, we have two
other terms.
M
plus five star m.
Do I have that right? Yes.
Let me give you an example.
Let's consider the probability that we
get to the symmetric point over here.
For the symmetric point, we might
imagine that's zero. That's m equals 0.
m equals 0. We might imagine that s and
ph are equal to each other. Why? Because
one of them corresponds to going through
the upper hole. The other one
corresponds to going through the lower
hole. But by symmetry, we might just
assume that the amplitude to go from
here to here is the same as the
amplitude to go from here to here. And
it would be. And in that case, cyan phi
would be the same. In other words, if we
went if we plugged in zero over here,
the probability to get right to here
to the central point
0 0,
the whole answer is four times the
probability
that you would just go through the upper
hole if only the upper hole was open.
Now, that's odd. You would have expected
classically just twice the probability
if you opened up both holes. You would
expect that the answer would be twice
the probability to get to here, not four
times the probability to get to here.
But what you get in quantum mechanics in
this case is four times the probability.
And the reason is because you add up the
amplitudes and then square.
If the amplitudes are equal and you
square, you'll get four times the
probability.
That's a little bit odd. All right,
maybe it's not that odd, but let me give
you something even odder.
By putting in the right um little
apparatus over here, you could change
you could make changes in the system.
Basically, just a little uh
potential or something that would have a
little bit of effect on the electron as
it went from here to here. It could have
the effect of changing the sign.
It could have the effect of changing the
sign. If it changed the sign,
it would also change this one.
In that case, if s of 0 was equal to
five of 0. They would cancel
and you would find zero probability to
get to this point over here. This is
destructive interference. The four was
constructive interference. zero is
destructive interference.
And what does it say? It says that there
are situations where with a certain
probability you would get to here going
through the upper route. With an equal
probability,
you would get to here going through the
lower route. But if you open up both
roots, you make it impossible to get to
here. Okay, that is a that's at least to
for my money that is as odd as the bell
inequality
that uh that by opening up you would
think you make it easier to get to here
and in fact you completely block out the
possibility of getting to here if
you start with a minus sign here.
But the minus sign doesn't affect either
of the probabilities for the upper root
or the lower root. It only affects what
happens when both roots are open. When
both roots are open, becomes completely
impossible to get to here. Despite the
fact that if you only open one route,
lock this one off, you can get to here.
Lock this one off, you can get to here.
Equal probabilities. Open them both, no
electron will ever get to this point
over here. That's destructive
interference.
So it's clear that probabilities in
quantum mechanics are not doing the
things that they do in classical
mechanics.
Can I can I ask a question about that?
Let regarding locality. Let's suppose
those two holes of one and minus one
were some distance apart and you could
uh in in a time less than it would take
light to go from one to the other. Turn
on that little uh field uh uh so that
you would change it from constructive to
to destructive interference in a very
short amount of time. So that when an
electron was going uh from the source to
the middle screen it it would might be
constructive but then on just as it was
getting there it would be turned to
destructive
and then you would accumulate the
results. In other words, you're changing
the experiment so fast that you can't
the electron would couldn't know. Uh I I
think my my my thought is even if you
change it fast you would still get the
proper result
such as you know you have interfer you
have
well I would I would say to change the
sign you might want to do something in
in the leg over here.
Right.
All right. Right. So right you could do
it while it's in flight but then it
would depend on whether you made the
change before the electron got to here
or after the electron passed it
just right prior to it. But but in in in
a smaller amount of time.
So the electron is over here.
Yes. But but and so that when you make
that change there that nothing could
propagate at the speed of light to the
other other slit
over here to the other slit. Yes. No.
No. I think if you make the change
before the electron gets here, you've
made the change,
right?
And that uh and that will change the
sign here, right?
That will change the sign.
I think his point is in a delayed choice
type of an experiment where you open
close the slit in a random way that
would wouldn't permit uh a somehow the
correlation to be set up at the other
split. The quantum mechanical result is
still going to hold classically you
would have to have some kind of in order
to get the correlation that you actually
meant to find out. We have no
correlation here. Just a probability.
Just a pure probability on the side. A
probability distribution.
Right? It's not just that the
probability depends on whether there's
one slit or two slits. Of course it
does. It's that the probabilities don't
add.
It's the probabilities don't add. The
amplitudes add. The probabilities don't
add. You get a probability in either
case depending on that sign four times
bigger than uh than the probability to
go through one opening with the other
one closed or just zero.
Right? But you can come back and decide
and figure out which which way
you know which of the two wave functions
uh was the actual description at the
time and you would find the results.
Um the distribution that you get
corresponds to the to that
what the the thing that you discover
later on is the actual situation at the
time.
It's a choice experiment where you think
where you don't know what you're going
to do until you actually until it
actually happens. So whether it's a plus
or a minus sign depends on some some
setup of the system which is uh space
flight separated from the other part of
the system and then later on you go and
go back and reconstruct what happened. I
think I think I think you have to give a
more precise setup in order uh I'm
trying to trying to study very you know
reasonably precise setups and we would
have to investigate each one separately
but what I really wanted to get to we'll
see if we can get to it I don't know
we're probably going to come back to it
is what happens if somebody over here if
there's an apparatus over here which
monitors which which way the electron
goes through which measures and records
which way the electron goes through.
This is the interesting question here. I
have assumed that nobody has recorded
which way the electron has gone through.
So at the end of experiment
you can't really say the electron went
through here or it went through here.
You don't know which way it went through
and there's no there's no clear notion
of being able to check afterwards that
the electron went through the upper or
the lower hole. But supposing you set
the problem up in a way that afterwards
you can check there's something which
records whether the electron goes
through the upper hole or the lower
hole. Then what happens to the
probability distribution? Well, you
might think well who cares whether you
whether you measure it or not. careful.
Measure it in such a way that doesn't
disturb anything very much. Do some very
minimal gentle detection of the electron
whether it goes through there or not.
You shouldn't disturb the system very
much. But in quantum mechanics, it's not
always possible to do minimal gentle
experiments.
And if you do an experiment which does
record which way the electron goes, you
will change the answers in a rather
dramatic way and basically destroy this
interference. Basically destroy either
the positive interference or the
negative interference. And so let me
show you how that works. And this is an
issue of entanglement.
This is entanglement of the electron
with the apparatus which measures it.
So let's invent an apparatus.
It's a very simple apparatus. When the
electron goes through the upper hole,
let's just put an upper hole over here,
a lower hole over here. Electron either
goes this way or it goes over here. And
here's my assumption. If the electron
passes by this hole, well, we're going
to put an apparatus. The apparatus is
going to be very simple. It's going to
be a spin. It's either up or down.
This spin is either up or down along the
third axis.
We're going to start with a spin down.
If the electron goes through the upper
hole here, it records its presence by
spinning by by flipping the spin up.
If it goes through the lower hole, it
does nothing for the electron.
This is the apparatus which records
which way the uh the electron goes. One
extra spin. It could be another electron
or it could just be some abstract system
with two states.
And if the electron goes through the
upper hole here, it records its presence
by flipping the spin to up.
Right? Let's do that problem. I think we
can I think we we'll see if we can get
the problem done. But we will go through
it again. I think because it's a it's
it's probably the most interesting. Um,
you put detector in the other hole.
What's that?
You put a detector.
We could put a detector in the other
hole, too. But, uh, but I don't think we
need a detector in the other hole
because if it doesn't go through here,
it does go through here. So, uh, we
would have a funny situation. We would
have a very funny situation if we put a
detector at both places and both of them
didn't record, but the electron got over
to here. So presumably that's forbidden.
You really only need a detector in one
place to tell you that the electron
either did go through here or it didn't
go through here
because it's an electron. Electron can't
go through both. It's not big enough to
go through both. If it goes through one
or the other, right?
If you measure it, it will go through
one or the other. Right? If you monitor
it, you will find that it goes through
one or the other. If you don't monitor
it, there's no way that you can know
which one it went through. If you do
monitor it at the end, you can go back
and check that electron. Now, you could
put another one over here too and
analyze it, but that way we have two
electrons and it gets a more complicated
apparatus, but we could certainly do it.
Be fun to do it and see what we get.
But, uh,
okay. So, let's then start. We start
with the electron over here.
It starts in the state zero.
But that's not enough information. We
also have to specify the state of the
spin. So now this is a composite system
composed of two parts. The electron
which can be at any one of these sites
but happens to start at zero and the
spin. And the spin starts down.
So let's put in the coordinate of the
spin here. That's the initial state.
Spin down electron at zero.
The electron comes over to here. Now
what happens if it goes through the
upper state? Let's close off this one
and forget it for a moment. If it goes
through the upper upper configuration,
then the electron comes out or the
configuration of the whole system.
Forget the electron. The whole system
then comes out in the state one. That's
because this is position number one.
This is position number minus one.
It comes out one. But what happens to
the electron to the um spin? It's up.
So if we go through the upper hole, the
state of the system is one up. What
happens if we go through the lower hole?
I hate this notation. One and minus one.
I should not have done that. Minus one
and down. I'll put a comment in there.
What happens if I open both holes?
If I open both holes by the linearity of
quantum mechanics, the state that comes
out the other side here is the sum of
these two
plus configuration of electron at minus
one with spin down.
So by the time the electron comes out or
the electron arrives at this point, it
arrives at this point and again we have
a superp position of states but notice
that it's entangled. Now the position of
the electron has become entangled with
the spin. It's very much like down up
plus up down. We have an entanglement
between the recording apparatus and the
uh and the whether the electron went
through the upper hole or the lower
hole.
That's what a measurement is. It's a
it's a entanglement between the
apparatus and the apparatus is just an
electron spin here and the system. The
system being uh the position of the
electron that went through.
Now what happens after that? What
happens by the time it gets over to the
screen over here?
Yeah.
Blackboard.
Well, let's assume that nothing happens
to the spin. If the spin is up, it's up
and it stays up. But the electron
proceeds to do exactly what it would
have done after it passes through here.
All right, let's assume that that it
just continues on its way leaving the
spin up. But remember previously one
went to summation over n sin n.
That's what we found over here.
Well, if nothing happens to the spin
during the journey of the electron over
to here, we can just stick in the spin
coordinate and just uh
say
electron in the upper configuration with
the spin up evolves exactly as it did
before without the spin doing anything.
The spin just stays up.
What happens if we start with the
electron in the lower state here? That
was minus one.
that evolved into some fi subn
n.
But now we should put in the coordinate
of the spin d.
What happens if both roots are open? If
both roots are open
then the final state is sum on n
s n with n up plus f n with n down.
Again it's an entangled state. the uh
the
coordinates of the position of the
electron are entangled with the
apparatus with the upness and the
downness. We can now calculate I'm
getting a little bit tired. I think uh
we'll probably go on next week. But
here's the problem. What is the
probability that we arrive at a
particular n?
Now we have a different situation. We
have two orthogonal possibilities for
the spin.
Okay. To calculate Well, I'm I'm going
to quit now because I think I think I've
probably given you more than enough for
tonight. Here's our problem. To
calculate the probability that we've
arrived at the M site, in particular,
the probability that we've arrived at
the origin, zero.
Anybody know what the answer is going to
be?
just the sum of the two. And the reason
is there are no cross terms because the
cross terms involve the inner product of
a down with an up. The inner product of
a down with an up is zero. The cross
terms won't be there anymore because
when we go to calculate the
probabilities, ups and downs are
orthogonal to each other and the cross
terms will not be there. I'm going to go
through this. We'll go through this in
detail. We'll use projection operators.
I don't know. We'll do it a dozen
different ways. But what you will see is
that the presence of the recording
device over here destroys the
interference. So if you actually did a
measurement to determine which way the
electron went, then probabilities would
add as they do in classical physics.
It's only if you don't record which way
the electron goes. So that nobody will
ever know. So that there's no record
left in the system of which way the
electron went that uh that the
interference takes place.
But the message for the moment just for
the moment is that making a measurement
is establishing entanglement
between a device and the system. It's
establishing entanglement between the
device and the system. And in this case
where is it? uh
adding these up, adding the state
vectors up
has an entanglement between whether
you're at one and minus one and whether
the electron spin or whether the spin
degree of freedom is up or down. So uh
and
the destruction of the interference is
what is called the collapse of the wave
function. In particular, it's the
collapse of the interference part of the
wave of the probabilities. The part
which has to do with the cross terms
between the size and the size.
They're destroyed by the measurement.
In the experiment you did before, before
you you flip the spin to label whether
it went through the top or the bottom.
Yeah.
You had a couple of entangled states
there also.
What's that?
You your your two states were entangled
there also
before we did what?
Before you changed the experiment so
that you were
we didn't have any we didn't all we had
was this.
Okay. Yeah. Or
All right. This state was exactly the
same as this state.
Okay. The state that those evolved from
is one plus minus one.
Right. There were no ups and downs
there.
Okay. You're not calling those
entanglements.
No, no, no, no, no, no, no. To have
entanglement, you have to have
entanglement with something.
No. Those aren't entangled. That's just
a simple superposition of states. Simple
superposition of states.
Yeah. There's only one system. There's
only one system and it's the electron
and it's in a superp position of states.
In the other case, there are two systems
electron and spin and the two systems
are entangled. You learn something about
one of them by looking at the other. So
you learn something about which orbit
you went through by looking at the uh by
looking at the spin. And then when you
have it interact with that that middle
screen there by flipping a span that
introduces another system or subsystem
or object into it.
Yes. It introduces another subsystem
into it and it introduces a system into
which into which the electron gets with
which the electron gets entangled. Okay.
It's that establishment of entanglement
between system and apparatus which
constitutes the measurement.
Yeah,
Professor Qu, let's imagine the same
setup and uh I mean it's it's physical.
So the hole at the top has I mean there
are a there are all sorts of atoms
around there. So there's always an
electron there. So, so, so couldn't an
electron just I mean in my in the
original case where you had interference
and an electron, you know, becomes
entangled with the the one that passed
it through.
What I'm trying to do is is separate the
you're asking you're asking
the knowledge verb and the and the
testing verbs from the physical the
physical apparatus.
Okay.
Yeah. Um I think what you're asking I I
think if I'm not mistaken supposing
these are real uh real things
can't this electron get entangled with a
uh with a with an atom in the uh in the
um yes the answer is it could and if it
does it destroys the interference
pattern.
So that's why you cool down your
apparatuses. That's why you don't uh you
don't want to have a lot of uh of gas
around that the electron can bump into.
Photons are not so bad because photons
don't interact very strongly with
anything. They're much more weakly
interacting than electrons. If you
really do it with electrons, an electron
passing through here, its electric
charge might disturb uh might disturb
something over here. And that
disturbance, if this disturbance was
enough, here's the here's the criteria.
If the disturbance is sufficient that
when you look at the disturbance
afterwards, you can tell definitely that
the electron went through the upper
slit, then you completely destroy the
interference pattern.
Now you might have a situation like
this. You might have a situation where
there's some degree of freedom in there
which initially had some probability
distribution which looks like this.
some degree of freedom in here position
of some atom or something and it has
some probability quantum probability
distribution that looks like this. The
electron goes through here.
If it shifts the probability
distribution so that it's not
overlapping then when you look
afterwards at the system you know yes no
whether it went through the upper one
and the lower one. You following me?
Right. Under that circumstance that will
destroy the interference pattern, but
there's a less severe situation where
the electron going through the upper
hole here may just shift the probability
distribution a little bit and then you
can't tell uniquely whether by looking
at the final situation where the
electron went through one hole or the
other hole. Then the interference
pattern will not be completely
destroyed.
decree.
It's a matter of decree. Yeah. It's a
matter of how much of a disturbance and
uh how much that disturbance tells you.
Now, if you really freeze things, make
them real cold and uh put everything
into its ground state so there's nothing
uh that is easily disturbed, then you
can create pretty much the idealized
situation where after you've gone
through there's just nothing that's been
recorded. uh in particular if the system
has an energy gap. If it takes some
energy to make an excitation in the
system to excite it or to disturb it and
the uh and the electron or the photon is
very low energy, it may not have enough
energy to make the disturbance in that
case you're you have the interference
pattern.
So it can be a question of energetics
whether if there's an energy gap that it
takes a certain minimum amount of energy
to disturb the system then uh then a low
energy photon or low energy electron
just can't disturb it and you would uh
and you would have the perfect
interference pattern.
So you get the interference pattern of a
single electron.
Well well you can't see an interfer you
can never see a probability distribution
with just one electron. But what you can
do is send one electron through at a
time. One electron through at a time.
Every 20 years you send an electron
through. And after many many electrons
go through, you look at the probability
distribution here. And it's the
probability distribution that has the
interference pattern. One electron just
goes blip somewhere. There's not much
you can read off that. Uh
yeah,
as always, an experiment always really
means a either repetition of the same
experiment over and over again or many
many identical experiments performed
simultaneously. But it means the
recording of statistics in in uh after
many events of the same kind. Right? So
you know to be clean about it and we
don't want to have to worry about two
electrons at the same time. We send the
electrons through once every 20 years
and make sure that they don't talk to
each other and don't give anything away
to each other. And uh
so the effect of of measurement is
always to destroy interference.
Yes.
It always has an effect of destroying
interference.
It destroys entanglement.
It destroys No, it creates entanglement.
Entanglement the measurement on the on
the on the screen.
Yeah.
After you deter it.
Which which particular yellow is bling
at?
Yeah. Once you right, right,
it destroys inter interference, it
creates entanglement.
It's the entanglement which corresponds
to the measurement itself. The formation
of entanglement, but once it becomes
entangled with the apparatus and you um
well, we'll talk more about measurement.
Talk more about
I don't think of the middle one as much
as the vapor.
It's just the fact you're letting it
interact with the uh with a metal set of
splits now by by magnetic field which is
changing the spin perhaps. But
you know you can do another measurement
over here.
We could do another measurement over
here and that measurement over here
would further collapse the wave function
and throw away some of the entanglement.
You're right. But this measurement over
here is the establishment of
entanglement. The second measurement
could be establishment of entanglement
with yet another system.
If we put another electron over here,
you know, it's a question of observers,
observing observers, observing
observers. We could even have an
electron which would a spin which would
monitor the spin over here.
Uh and um
it's sort of like you went through the
whole discussion exactly when it's
interacting with a metal screen.
Yeah. And it's you're changing perhaps a
spin, but you can do it a little bit,
you know, you can turn this thing from
zero to one. So that means you're
increasing the amount of entanglement.
Yes.
And that makes sense.
Yeah. You could you can you can turn up
the interaction between the electron and
the spin.
Uh so for example, if you had a very
weak interaction, then most of the time
that the electron went through, it would
not flip the spin.
Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. You could certainly
That's right. You can That's right.
That's right. We could uh make up some
other game, but the game that I made up
is that we did a complete measurement.
We did an accurate measurement that told
us whether we went through the upper
slit or the lower slit. Now, we can talk
about weaker measurements. Measurements
where we only get some partial
knowledge, where we find out
uh that it was more likely that it went
through the upper one than the lower
one. And your wave function here on the
other side will have states with down
and down.
That's right. That's right. Instead of
this one being up, there will be a piece
with a down and another piece with an
up. Right. And the one with a down might
be the bigger one, in which case you
mostly do have the interference. Yeah.
There are weaker and stronger
measurements.
[Music]
The preceding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.